{
  "reference_number": "2596",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "This target is not particularly important, as the process will be \"overtaken by events\" long before we get there."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The short lived (CH4) remains a part of the normal cycle."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is a reasonable way of managing change"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Never say never."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I cannot guess for certain, the reference is NOT there, but I doubt that the bill considers the indirect but most puissant threat to New\n\nZealand. The global enforcement of CO2 pricing which WILL happen, will cut OUR trade. We are on our own."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The most important THREAT to New Zealand is not directly from the destabilized climate. The most important (and ENTIRELY\nunavoidable) threat is from the actions taken globally to bring emissions under control. When a CO2 price becomes commonly\n\nenforced, and that WILL HAPPEN, our trade will be cut in half. We are not prepared for that."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I note the absence of an actual reference. The document summary does not have so many pages :-) There are a half dozen other\n\n(likely former sections of a larger doc) documents, I cannot guess. The desirable expertise needs to be there, just don't know what\nyou chose."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Emphatically - because this, more than anything, is the chief threat"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As before, I don't have the ability to find the reference."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It won’t hurt us all that much, will it? An Island in the middle of a big ocean? All the effects will be buffered by the ocean, won’t they?\nYup. Likely true for, though a lot of our infrastructure will end up underwater... in 100 years or so. Yet there is another inconvenient\n\ntruth that New Zealand is blind to. A devastatingly “inconvenient truth” that will be more serious for NZ than most places and will\narrive sooner. As the climate starts to unravel, and delivers regular shocks to the economic system, (very likely by 2030, certain by\n\n2035) the cost of CO2 will be forced above $100 per tonne. That’s a generational change, a recognition of peril, and a shift that will\naffect the whole world. There is no \"free trade\". There is no \"free\". At that level the price of fuel for shipping triples, the cost of\nshipping doubles, and our trade IS LESS THAN HALF ITS PREVIOUS LEVELS.!!! At their best the “free trade” agreements give us a 1 or\n\n2% incremental increase. Cutting trade in half isn’t thinkable here in NZ Yet it WILL HAPPEN! Whether we choose to prepare or not,\nclimate destabilization will affect trade and it will affect OUR trade more than anyone else’s because... ...we are further from\n\neverywhere than anyone else is. When we export wood and import wood furniture, we have damaged our economy and the\nenvironment. The benefit of the “cheaper” furniture does not offset the long term damage. When we export Apples and import\n\nApplesauce, we have damaged the economy and the environment just the same. When we allow industry to depend on foreign\nsuppliers of critical components, foreign suppliers at risk of failing as climate worsens, we damage our national security. Ricardo\n\nnever, in spite of the blunders in his treatise on \"comparative advantage\" pushed the notion that is common knowledge in New\nZealand today, that we should ONLY make the things we are good at. We can't afford to continue to believe that. The most important\nand difficult change? We have to change our minds. This is the LEAST step we can take, and it needs to be taken now."
    }
  ]
}
